<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor2_18112016.xsd">
    
    <page filename="PrincetonPA6452.535v.tif" reader="Harvey" signature="[S3v]"/>
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="left_margin">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Liuij mors.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                Livy's death.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="tail">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Pla[e]runq[ue] vnius anni consulatu, plus gestum seriorum negotiorum, egregiorumq[ue]
                        facinorum, quàm tota vita maximorum Regum: exceptis admodùm paucis; Cyro, Philippo, Alexandro, Pyrrho; 
                        Agesilao, Euagora, Eumene; Jugurtha, Mithridate: alijs perpaucis. Olim plus virtutis, minus fama[e]: hodie plus fama[e], minus 
                        virtutis. Egregiè Romanus Poeta, ex ipsius Ca[e]saris disciplina: breue, et irreparabile tempus, Omnibus est vita[e]: 
                        sed Famam extendere Factis, Hoc Virtutis opus.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Cyrus the Great"/> <!--Could also be Cyrus the Younger-->
                    <person name="Philip II of Macedon"/> <!--It is probably this Philippus Harvey is talking about in this marginal note, since he mentioned this king earlier in the Livy-->
                    <person name="Alexander the Great"/>
                    <person name="Pyrrhus of Epirus"/>
                    <person name="Agesilaus II"/>
                    <!--Unclear which Evagoras Harvey is talking about-->
                    <person name="Eumenes of Cardia"/>
                    <person name="Jugurtha"/>
                    <person name="Mithridates VI of Pontus"/> <!--Probably Harvey is mentioning this person, since he does so elsewhere in the Livy-->
                    <X-ref book_title="Aeneid" language="LA" person="Virgil" text="famam extendere factis, hoc virtutis opus"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <language ident="EL">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="tail">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        σός λόγος ἐργον ἐμοῖο.
                    </marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                In a consulate of one year generally more serious business and excellent deeds are accomplished than in the entire life of the greatest kings, 
                with very few exceptions: Cyrus, Philip, Alexander, Pyrrhus, Agesilaus, Evagoras, Eumenes, Jugurtha, Mithridates, and extremely few others. 
                Once there was more virtue, less fame; today there is more fame, less virtue. Based on the discipline of Caesar himself, 
                the Roman poet put it brilliantly: "the course of life is brief and cannot be recalled: but virtue’s task is this, to increase fame by deeds" 
                [ trans. Kline]. Your word, my deed.            
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
                
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="tail">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Scire Gra[e]ca[e], Romanaeq[ue] historia[e]; continuatam seriem, valde conducit polyhistori. 
                        Herodotus historiam suam est orsus à fine prophetarum: Thucydides à fine Herodoti: Xenophon à fine Thucydidis. 
                        Romanae historiae primam partem praecipue suscepit Halicarnasseus; professus eam se historiam velle producere vsq[ue] 
                        ad initium primi belli Punici. Secundam partem antèa suscepit Polybius. Postèa Liuius tertiam potissimùm partem explicare voluit.
                        Tacitus non procul à fine Liuij suos Annales orditur: Marcellinus à fine Taciti, id est, à principatu Nerua[e]: 
                        vt Herodianus ab exitu M. Antonini, in quo desijt Dion. Nec est difficile, talia continua[e] successionis exempla in 
                        alijs pla[e]risq[ue] historicis obseruare.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Herodotus"/>
                    <person name="Thucydides"/>
                    <person name="Xenophon"/>
                    <person name="Dionysius of Halicarnassus"/>
                    <person name="Polybius"/>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                    <person name="Tacitus"/>
                    <person name="Marcellinus"/>
                    <person name="Herodian"/>
                    <person name="Mark Antony"/>
                    <person name="Cassius Dio"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                It is tremendously profitable for the polyhistor to know the continuous line of Greek and Roman history. Herodotus began his history 
                from the end of the prophets; Thucydides from the end of Herodotus; Xenophon from the end of Thucydides. Dionysius of Halicarnassus took up 
                the first part of Roman history in particular, declaring he wanted to record history up to the beginning of the first Punic war. 
                Before, Polybius took on the second part. Afterwards Livy wanted to give an account of the third part especially. Tacitus begins his Annals 
                not far from the end of Livy. Marcellinus from the end of Tacitus, namely from the principate of Nerva, just as Herodian starts from the 
                death of Marcus Antoninus, where Cassius Dio stopped. And it is not hard to notice such examples of continued succession in most of the other 
                historians.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="tail">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Duo autem Romana[e] historia[e] doctissimi, et diligentissimi scriptores, Dionysius, et Liuius. Quod attinet ad res, et tempora, 
                        Dionysij antefero diligentiam: verba à Liuio malo repetere, et sententias. Neq[ue] enim minima historia[e], ipsiusq[ue] iurisprudentia[e] 
                        Romana[e] pars, visq[ue] sita est in ipsis formulis; quas vbiq[ue] Liuius diserte recitat, atq[ue] adeo religiosè: Dionysius, et 
                        reliqui Gra[e]ci sua lingua exprimere non possent, né si vellent quidem maximè. Vnde Politicum decet, in primisq[ue] iurisconsultum, 
                        Liuiana[e] phrasis maximè omnium esse obseruantem: vt postèa Tacitea[e]. In qua Romana[e] prudentia[e], et fortitudinis; temperantia[e] 
                        etiam, et iustitia[e] proprius quidam vigor, visq[ue] neruosa, viuidiùs mihi videtur efflorescere, adeóq[ue] fertiliùs maturescere. 
                        Doctor Gentilis totus est Liuianus: vt Lipsius ferè Taciteus. Ambo sapiunt: sed vterq[ue] coniunctus, varieq[ue] coagmentatus plus 
                        valeret. Ta[e]det omnis sine varietate excellentia[e]: et philosophi est, plura bona paucioribus anteponere.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Dionysius of Halicarnassus"/>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                    <person name="Tacitus"/>
                    <person name="Alberico Gentili"/>
                    <person name="Lipsius"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                Yet the two most learned and assiduous writers of Roman history [are] Dionysius and Livy. In regard to the subject and the times I esteem 
                Dionysius’ attentiveness more highly; I prefer to repeat the words and thoughts of Livy. For in these very formulas lies quite a big part of 
                Roman history and of jurisprudence itself, which Livy recites dexterously and indeed religiously. Dionysius and the other Greeks could not 
                have expressed them in their language, even if they had very much wanted to do so. And for this reason it is appropriate for the politician, 
                and especially the lawyer, to be attentive most of all to Livy’s diction, just like afterwards to that of Tacitus. In this a particular 
                vitality and powerful force of Roman prudence and courage, of restraint also and of justice seems to me to flourish in quite a lively way, 
                and indeed to come to maturity in a very fruitful manner. Doctor Gentili is completely of Livy, just as Lipsius more or less of Tacitus.
                Both are wise, but each of them is stronger when connected and in various ways fastened together. Without variety every form of excellence 
                makes weary, and it is the task of the philosopher to place a greater quantity of excellence before a smaller one.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Germanicus Caesar" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Suetonius in" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Sex. Pompeius" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Claudius Tiberius Caesar" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Vitellio" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Tiberius Nero Caesar" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Germanicus Caesar" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="T.Liuij historiographi mors" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Valerius Messala" type="straight"/>
        <underline language="LA" method="pen" text="Aurelius Cotta" type="straight"/>
        
        <symbol name="SS" place="intext"/>
        
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Caligula-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Caesar-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Vitellio-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Caesar III-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Caesar II-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Syllanus-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Balbus-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Eusebio-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--SS symbol-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Messala-->
        <mark method="pen" name="dot" place="intext"/> <!--Cotta-->
        
        <mark language="LA" method="pen" name="plus_sign" place="intext" text="Tiberius Nero"/> 
        <mark language="LA" method="pen" name="plus_sign" place="intext" text="Germanicus Caesar"/> 
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>
