<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor2_18112016.xsd">
    
    <page filename="HoughtonSTC11402.002v.tif" pagination="[Aiii[v]]" reader="Harvey"/>
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="head">
                    <marginalia_text>Qui Hominum, Rerumq[ue] Artem habet, solus est maximarum Actionum Executor.</marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>He who holds the skills of men and matter, is the sole performer of the greatest actions.</translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="90" place="left_margin">
                    <marginalia_text>In hominum, rerumq[ue] Sympathijs, et Antipathijs, peritè, diligenterq[ue] vtendis; Illa Miraculoru[m] Ars, quam mihi animus pollicetur.
                    Ars Hominu[m], constat tribus fer[e] Artibus, Ethica, Politica, et Eloquentia: Ars rerum, tribus item Artibus, Physica, Mathematica, et Mechanica. 
                    Nihil valet, sine quotidiana praxi, et acerrima panurgia: nec vlla quidem praxis multùm potest, sine inuicta, et infinita Audatia: Vnde ad</marginalia_text>
                </position>
                <position book_orientation="90" place="tail">
                    <marginalia_text>Tria mea Elementa perpetuò  recurrendu[m], peritiam, Assuetudine[m], Zelum:
                    qua[e] dictis, fastisq[ue] potentib[us] operant[u]r miracula.</marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>Skillfully and diligently is using the sympathies and antipathies of men and things.
                That art of miracles, which the mind promises me. The art of men generally corresponds to three sciences: Ethics, Politics, and Eloquence.  The art of things likewise corresponds to three sciences: Physics, Mathematics and Engineering.
                Nothing prevails without daily action and most vigorous craft; nor indeed can any action be much, without invincible and infinite audacity. 
                And so to my three elements that must always return: skill, practice, zeal: through these powerful words and deeds miracles can be achieved.
            </translation> 
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="270" place="right_margin">
                    <marginalia_text>Reuerâ Talis sis, qualis videri affectas. Solidum gloria[e] fundamentu[m].</marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>In fact, be so, like you desire to be seen. The real foundation of glory.</translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <underline language="EN" method="pen" text="syr Nycolas Carowe," type="straight"/>
        
        <symbol name="SS" place="head"/>
        <symbol name="SS" place="head"/>
        
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>
