<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 tei_ms.xsd">
  <!-- the element locus always refers to a folio number; it may have @to and @from to designate a sequence of folia -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Roman de la Rose</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>MSEL</distributor>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note rend="IDENTIFICATION">
          <p>MS Codex 906, Philadelphia, PA, University of Pennsylvania (olim MS French 1).
                     French, last quarter of the fifteenth century. Contains
                     <hi rend="italics">Roman de la Rose</hi> (folios <locus from="1" to="340">1-340</locus>).</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="BASIC INFORMATION">
          <p>Paper, 300 x 210 mm
                  340 folios. (Modern foliation begins on fol. <locus>2</locus>, i.e.
                  fol. <locus>2</locus> labeled “1” in modern hand – since foliation skips fol. <locus>318</locus>,
                  count comes out the same by end.) </p>
        </note>
        <note rend="MATERIAL">
          <p><material>Paper</material>, in good condition aside from worm/insect holes through first couple of
                  quires. The first nineteen quires contain numerous examples of a watermark
                  matching Briquet 1799. Quire XX, copied by a different scribe, contains Briquet
                  1548 and 1701. Quire XXI contains a watermark very similar to Briquet 1546, with
                  the exception that the three “arrows” are simply straight lines with no points on
                  the end, as well as another watermark not found in Briquet.</p>
          <p>Briquet numbers from C. M. Briquet, <hi rend="italics">Les Filigranes:
                     Dictionnaire Historique des Marques du Papier dès leur Apparition vers 1282
                     jusqu'en 1600.</hi> 4 vols. New York: Hacker Art Books, 1966:</p>
          <p>1799: “31X44. Toulouse, 1474. A. MUN., CC. 1106 : <hi rend="italics">Pièces à l’appui des cptes</hi>.”</p>
          <p>1548: “31X44. Châteaudun, 1463. A. EURE-ET-LOIR, E. 2739: <hi rend="italics">Tabellionage</hi>. Var. ident. : Blois, 1466; Poitiers, 1466-74;
                  Bretagne, 1472.”</p>
          <p>1701: “31,5X44. Châteaudun, 1454. A. EURE-ET-LOIR, E. 2734. : <hi rend="italics">Tabellionage</hi>. Var. ident. : Orleans, 1457;
                  Châteaudun, 1457-65; Champagne (Sarthe), 1458; Angers, 1464</p>
          <p>1546: “31X44. Châteaudun, 1457. IBID. E. 2735 : <hi rend="italics">id.</hi> Var. simil. : Blois, 1496.</p>
          <p>On the basis of this evidence, we are able to establish a <hi rend="italics">terminus a quo</hi> for the manuscript of 1474. It is interesting to note,
                  however, that quires XX and XXI are on paper dating as much as twenty years prior
                  to this time, and that each is the work of a different scribe. </p>
        </note>
        <note rend="QUIRES">
          <p>Bound in gatherings of 16 with the exception of quire XIX. No quire numbers.
                  Signatures at bottom right; note that signature <hi rend="italics">a</hi> begins
                  on fol. 2 (the first folio with text), and thus runs ai-avii (i.e. not ai-aviii,
                  which one would expect in a quire of 16 leaves). Alphabet does not include <hi rend="italics">j</hi> in labeling quires. Quire XX, where there is a change of
                  hand, simply numbers first eight leaves i-viij, as does XXI (where there is
                  another change of hand). Quire XXI is also numbered, although there is no apparent
                  need for this since it is a bifolium. Catchwords at bottom center, often cropped.</p>
          <list>
            <item n="I">
              <locus from="1" to="16">1-16</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="II">
              <locus from="17" to="32">17-32</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="III">
              <locus from="33" to="48">33-48</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="IV">
              <locus from="49" to="64">49-64</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="V">
              <locus from="65" to="80">65-80</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="VI">
              <locus from="81" to="96">81-96</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="VII">
              <locus from="97" to="112">97-112</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="VIII">
              <locus from="113" to="128">113-128</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="IX">
              <locus from="129" to="144">129-144</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="X">
              <locus from="145" to="160">145-160</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XI">
              <locus from="161" to="176">161-176</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XII">
              <locus from="177" to="192">177-192</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XIII">
              <locus from="193" to="208">193-208</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XIV">
              <locus from="209" to="224">209-224</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XV">
              <locus from="225" to="240">225-240</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XVI">
              <locus from="241" to="256">241-256</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XVII">
              <locus from="257" to="272">257-272</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XVIII">
              <locus from="273" to="288">273-288</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XIX"><locus from="289" to="306">289-306</locus>(gathering of 18 rather than 16 leaves)</item>
            <item n="XX">
              <locus from="307" to="322">307-322</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XXI">
              <locus from="323" to="338">323-338</locus>
            </item>
            <item n="XXII">
              <locus from="339" to="340">339-340</locus>
            </item>
          </list>
          <p>i + 340 + i. Bound in gatherings of 16 with the exception of quire XIX. No quire numbers. Signatures at bottom right; note that signature a begins on fol. <locus>2</locus> (the first folio with text), and thus runs ai-avii (i.e. not ai-aviii, which one would expect in a quire of 16 leaves).  Alphabet does not include j in labeling quires.  Quire XX, where there is a change of hand, simply numbers first eight leaves i-viij, as does XXI (where there is another change of hand). Quire XXII is also numbered, although there is no apparent need for this since it is a bifolium.  Catchwords at bottom center, often cropped. Modern foliation begins on fol. <locus>2</locus>, i.e. fol. <locus>2</locus>labeled “1” in modern hand – since foliation skips fol. <locus>318</locus>, count comes out to 340, which is accurate, by the end. In this description, pages are numbered sequentially beginning with fol. <locus>1r</locus>, as indicated in the collation.</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="LAYOUT">
          <p>Ruled in drypoint, with only four lines to define text block; no ruling for
                  individual lines of verse. No prickings. Single text block with one column of text
                  per leaf; text block varies in size, usually 190mm x 100-110mm. Usually 33-35
                  lines in first twenty quires; 31-34 in quire XX; 31-33 in quire XXI; 33-37 lines
                  in XXII.</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="SCRIPT">
          <p>The main scribal hand, using brown ink and a cursiva script, is responsible for
                  the first nineteen quires. A second hand copied quire XX; XXI in a hand similar to
                  main scribe, but likely a third scribe. Lines following rubricated initials use a
                  larger, slightly more formal script. Corrections are sparse, although there are a
                  few (see, e.g., lining through at bottom of fol. <locus>306</locus>). No running
                  heads.</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="DECORATION">
          <p>A number of rubricated headings throughout, usually with guide line written in
                  brown ink in the margin; these marginal guides often partially cropped. Numerous
                  two-line rubricated capitals throughout. The initial of each line (other than
                  two-line rubricated initials) touched in yellow.</p>
          <p>No line fillers. There are no miniatures or illuminations, but spaces
                  approximately nine lines in height were left for them; these are frequent in the
                  beginning of the manuscript, but become progressively less so and eventually
                  disappear.</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="BINDING">
          <p>Blind-stamped contemporary calf, rebacked (Zacour – Hirsch). No clasps or metallic
                  pieces. One paper flyleaf each at beginning and end, thus i + 340 + i. Title on
                  spine: “LE ROMAN DE LA ROSE” “DE JEAN MEUN DIT CLOPINEL” “MANUSCRIPT DU XV ?
                  [S]IECLE.” Parchment binding fragment shows between folios <locus>338</locus> and
                     <locus>339</locus>.</p>
        </note>
        <note rend="HISTORY">
          <p>According to the University of Pennsylvania catalog entry, “Sold in the Ashburnham
                  collection at auction at Sotheby’s, 10 June 1901, lot 607,” and “Purchased from
                  Librairie J. Thiebaud, 1950.” Written on inside front cover: “Archives du
                  Bibliophile XV Bulletin No.” and a signature that Zacour-Hirsch transcribe
                  “Marcel(?).” On folio 2r: “Delaplanches.” A scrap of paper containing verses
                  64-73, apparently by main scribe’s hand is pasted on fol. 1.</p>
          <p>Previous descriptions:</p>
          <p>Zacour, Norman P. and Rudolf Hirsch. <hi rend="italics">Catalogue of Manuscripts
                     in the Libraries of the University of Pennsylvania to 1800.</hi> Philadelphia:
                  U of Pennsylvania P, 1965. p. 54.</p>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Archives du bibliophile; ou, Bulletin de l'amateur de livres et
                     du libraire. Bulletin XV.</hi>
          </p>
          <p>See also call number “Ms. Codex 906” in the Penn Libraries Catalog, available
                  online.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
          <p>Description by Timothy L. Stinson</p>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <note type="format">manuscript</note>
          <note type="commonName">Penn Codex 906</note>
          <title>Roman de la Rose</title>
          <extent>
            <measure quantity="340" unit="folios">340 folios</measure>
            <dimensions>
              <height unit="mm">300</height>
              <width unit="mm">210</width>
            </dimensions>
          </extent>
          <note type="illustrations">0</note>
          <note type="material">paper</note>
          <pubPlace>France</pubPlace>
          <date notAfter="1500" notBefore="1475">15th century</date>
        </bibl>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Philadelphia, PA</settlement>
            <repository>University of Pennsylvania Library</repository>
            <idno>Codex 906</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <msItem n="1">
              <locus from="2r" to="340v">2r-340v</locus>
              <title>Roman de la Rose</title>
              <note type="textid">rose</note>
              <note type="folios">339</note>
              <note type="illustrations">0</note>
              <note type="linesPerColumn">37</note>
              <note type="leavesPerGathering">16</note>
              <note type="columnsPerFolio">1</note>
              <note type="author">Guillaume de Lorris</note>
              <note type="author">Jean de Meun</note>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div> </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
