<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor2_18112016.xsd">
    
<page filename="PrincetonK6233.frontmatter.flyleaf.025r.tif" reader="Harvey"/>
    <annotation>
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="full_page"> 
                    <marginalia_text>
                        L. Valla, quinquaginta Digestorum libros expeditè, curioseq[ue] perlegit suo Marte, Sine
                        ullis glossis, aut doctoribus antiquis, aut nouis. Quid ni alius faciat pari acuite, aut 
                        pra[e]gnantiori compendio? Pra[e]sertim subtiliori dialectica, et pra[e]dentiori politica pra[e]munitus,
                        idemq[ue] omni eleganti literatura vel a[e]qualis, vel fortassis instructior. Expedit autem tali 
                        Pandectologo, ab istis ordiri analyticis Freigij Paratitlis: tumq[ue] ipsum continuò iuris ciuilis
                        textum verè aureum dialecticè, politicè, iuridicè retexere, intimè
                        examinare, priuatim, publicéq[ue] disputare, assiduissimè repetere: memoria[e] penitùs
                        infigere: nunq[uam] nimis quod nunq[uam] satis. Certè ha[e]c Pandectarum Synopsis instar est
                        adamantini speculi, ad totius iuris Romani corpus, et animam conspicua analyse pra[e]monstrandam.
                        Qua[e] omnium est humanaru[m] professionu[m] Vtilissima, atq[ue] potentissima, non modò 
                        prudentissima, et honoratissima.
                        Nec verò vlla ciuilis ars, scientia, aut facultas tanti est in rep. momenti, aut in mundo pretij,
                        quanti ista forensis, et pragmatica disciplina, maximè omnium regia professio. Cui radicitùs
                        enucleandas quadruplici opus analyse, generali logica, speciali politica, particulari iuridica, singulari 
                        pragmatica. Tantum nactus Spartam, hanc perornato.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Lorenzo Valla"/>
                    <person name="Johann Thomas Freigius"/>
                    <book title="Digest"/>
                    <book title="Paratitla seu synopsis pandectarum iuris ciuilis"/>
                    <X-ref book_title="De elegantiis Latinae Linguae" person="Lorenzo Valla"/>
                    <X-ref book_title="Adagia" language="LA" person="Erasmus" text="Spartam nactus es, hanc orna"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                Lorenzo Valla read quickly and curiously through the fifty books of the 'Digest' on his own, without any glosses,
                either from ancient or modern scholars. What could another not do with a comparable acuity or more pregnant
                compendium? Particularly if he were fortified with a more subtle dialectic and more compact politics, and
                either equally or perhaps better trained in all elegant literature. Instead, in the study of the 'Digest' he rushes
                from these to begin with Freigius's analytical 'Paratitla'. And then immediately to rework this truly golden text of 
                civil law dialectically, politically and juridically, to examine it intimately, to discuss it publically and 
                privately, and to return to it assiduously. Inwardly, he fixes it in his memory. Never too much, but never enough. 
                Certainly, this synopsis of the 'Digest' is the image of an incorruptible mirror, to be directed, with its striking 
                analysis, at the body and spirit of all Roman law. Of all human professions, this is the most useful and most 
                powerful, as well as wisest and most honourable. Any civil art, science or skill only serves for the progress 
                of the state or the wealth of the world to the extent that it is a public and pragmatic discipline; this is
                particularly the case when it comes to the king of all professions. Fundamentally, the task involves a fourfold 
                analysis: by general logic, specific policies, particar laws and individual cases.
                "You are in Sparta; make it splendid."
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <!-- JG: Finalised transcription, but some more research is necessary. It might be that Harvey is quoting this passage from a work by Valla. See: The Universities of the Italian Renaissance
By Paul F. Grendler; https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=UcmTz4j-XIIC&pg=PT361&lpg=PT361&dq=lorenzo+valla+digest&source=bl&ots=x3HI06dDEO&sig=Qb0IRBYNWOl_xWg8pe3g14G7dFg&hl=en&sa=X&ved=0ahUKEwi-qL3LwePLAhXCjg8KHdG8BJYQ6AEIJzAC#v=onepage&q=lorenzo%20valla%20digest&f=false
        See Valla's 'Elegantiarum linguae latinae libri six, preface to book 3-->
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>
