<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor2_18112016.xsd">
    
    <page filename="PrincetonPA8550.endmatter.pastedown.tif" pagination="pastedown" reader="Harvey"/>
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="English_secretary">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position book_orientation="0" place="full_page">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        Te[m]peries circumambientis äeris modo uiuidiores 
                        efficit, modò hebetiores.
                        
                        Omnes paene Philosophi, et Astronomi consentiunt    
                        diuersas qualitates Eleme[n]toru[m], qua[e] in Planetis sunt, 
                        causam fuisse, cur hunc situm, et ordinem haberent, 
                        quem nu[n]c habent; vt stella Iouis, quae temperata 
                        est, poneretur inter Saturnu[m] frigidiorem, et Marte[m]
                        calidiore[m], quàm par est: Mars calidus, et siccus   
                        inter Iouem, et Venerem, iuxta Platonicos:
                        vt quod uocere possit nimiùm in vna stella,
                        tardetur contraria qualitate in altera.
                        
                        Antigui Astrologi, cu[m] scirent Solem in Cancro <!--JG: Partly taken from 'Wilhelm von Conches, De philosophia mundi?-->
                        terras adurere; uiderentq[ue] nihilominùs in aliq[uo]
                        anno hoc paru[m] contingere; intelligentes hoc ex
                        natura solis no[n] esse, qu[a]esiueru[n]t qu[a]ena[m] stella 
                        planetaru[m] esset in co[e]le[m] signo cu[m] sole,
                        [reput]entesq[ue] Saturnu[m], statuerunt eius
                        frigiditatem causam fuisse: quod postea
                        semper notatu[m] est, semel primò obseruatu[m].
                        animaduersu[m].
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <emphasis method="pen" text="obseruatu[m]." type="straight"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                The temperature of the surrounding air makes things at one moment more lively, at another more languid.           
                
                All philosophers and astronomers agreed that diverse qualities of the elements, found in the planets, was the cause why they had the position and order which they have now; so that the star of Jupiter, which was mild, was placed between Saturn, a colder planet, and Mars, a hotter one. Likewise, according to the
                platonists, Mars, hot and dry [is placed] between Jupiter and Venus. Thus, what could be called excessive in one star is checked by a contrary quality in another.
                
               The ancient astrologers, when they knew that the sun scorched the earth in the summer, but nevertheless saw that this did not happen in another year,
               they knew that this was not due to the nature of the Sun. They sought which star of the planets was in the sky with the sun's sign, and considering Saturn,
               they decided that this was the cause of the cold. What is always known later was first, at some point, noticed or observed.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>
